{"tossups": [{"question": "After the losing side of this conflict was forced to pay 450 million silver taels in compensation, the\u201cNew Policies\u201d were passed to boost tax revenue. Backlash against the Treaty of Tientsin helped prompt this conflict, in which a 55-day siege of the International Legations was ended by the arrival of the Eight Nation Alliance. The Empress Dowager Cixi [see-shee] supported a militia group against foreign missionaries in, for the point, what Chinese rebellion led by the Society of Righteous and Harmonious Fists?", "answer": "<b> Boxer</b> Rebellion (accept equivalents for Rebellion, like Uprising; accept<b> Yihetuan</b> Movement; accept answers mentioning the<b> Society of Righteous Harmony</b> movement before \u201cRighteous\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A two-year expedition mapping this river was led by Ernest Doudard de Lagr\u00b4ee, who died near Dali. This river is said to be home to serpents known as \u201cphayas,\u201d which locals believe are responsible for the Naga fireballs that seem to rise out of this river\u2019s water. When this river floods, low tides and flow reversals prompt it to flow into the Tonle [ton-lay] Sap. For the point, name this river that drains into the South China Sea after forming most of Laos\u2019 western border, the longest river in Southeast Asia.", "answer": "<b> Mekong</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One of these places was established in Lebadaea after a boy ended a plague by following some bees into a cave. The hero Trophonius named one of these places, another of which was built around an oak tree in Dodona. Gases and vapors from hot springs were used during a ritual at one of these places in which Pythia, a priestess of Apollo, would utter cryptic statements believed to predict the future. For the point, name these Greek religious sites such as Delphi.", "answer": "<b> oracle</b>s (accept Oracle of<b> Trophonius</b> before read; prompt on cave before \u201coak tree\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This man was the claimed target of a 2007 suicide bombing at Bagram Airport north of Kabul. This politician reversed a previous stance on the legalization of same-sex marriage, partially in support of his openly lesbian daughter, Mary. An aide of this man, Scooter Libby, resigned during the Valerie Plame scandal. In the 1990s, this man served as the CEO of Halliburton and as Secretary of Defense under George H.W. Bush. For the point, name this Wyoming politician who served as George W. Bush\u2019s vice president.", "answer": "Richard \u201cDick\u201d<b> Cheney</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This stadium will be the largest venue in use for the 2022 Winter Olympics, though Herzog, Meuron and Ai Weiwei originally designed it for use in the 2008 Summer Olympics. For the point, name this Beijing stadium that resembles a fowl\u2019s resting place.", "answer": "<b> Bird\u2019s Nest</b> (accept Beijing<b> National Stadium</b>; accept<b> Niaochao</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "In 1931, this party expelled its own Prime Minister after he formed a coalition with Stanley Baldwin. This party lost 40 seats in a 1924 election shortly after the publication of the Zinoviev letter, which embarrassed the aforementioned Ramsay MacDonald. This party implemented the National Health Service and other welfare programs under the leadership of Clement Attlee, who defeated Winston Churchill in the 1945 election. For the point, name this left-leaning political party in the United Kingdom.", "answer": "<b> Labour</b> Party", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "David Rizzio was accused of an affair with this woman; while she was seven months pregnant, Rizzio was stabbed 50 times in front of her by a mob led by Patrick Ruthven. This woman\u2019s Casket Letters implicated her in the explosion that killed her husband, Lord Darnley. This woman was executed after the discovery of the Babington Plot, which aimed to install her as the Catholic ruler of England. For the point, name this cousin and rival of Elizabeth I, the mother of James VI of Scotland.", "answer": "<b> Mary Stuart</b> (or<b> Mary, Queen of Scots</b>; accept<b> Mary I of Scotland</b>; prompt on Mary; do not accept or prompt on \u201cMary I\u201d alone, \u201cBloody Mary,\u201d or \u201cMary Tudor\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This composer wrote a piece for the Duke of Saxe-Wessenfels that includes the aria \u201cSheep may safely graze.\u201d This composer of the<em> Hunting Cantata</em> included two viola da gambas but no violins in the sixth and final work in a collection named for a German state. This composer\u2019s<em> Musical Offering</em> was based on a melody given to him by Frederick the Great. Felix Mendelssohn revived the music of, for the point, what Baroque composer of the<em> Brandenburg Concertos</em>?", "answer": "Johann Sebastian<b> Bach</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "During this period, Vasily Shuysky held power for four years. Marinka the Witch\u2019s first two marriages allowed Polish nobles to meddle during this period; her first husband was killed, cremated, and had his ashes shot out of a cannon in Poland\u2019s direction. That man was this period\u2019s first \u201cFalse Dmitri,\u201d an impostor claiming to be the son of Ivan the Terrible and the heir to the Rurik Dynasty. Boris Godunov ruled during, for the point, what complicated period of Russian history before the rise of the Romanovs?", "answer": "<b> Time of Troubles</b> (accept<b> Smutnoe vremya</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this war, a covert operation called Operation Tailwind relied on an escort of 12 Cobra gunships, which were alleged to have deployed sarin gas. The casualties in one battle of this war led James Spears to compare its machine gun fire to a hamburger machine. Hill 937 thus became known as Hamburger Hill in this war, during which Company C was commanded by William Calley during the My Lai Massacre. For the point, name this Southeast Asian war from which US forces withdrew shortly before the fall of Saigon.", "answer": "<b> Vietnam</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This government was allowed an \u201cArmy of the Armistice\u201d to protect overseas holdings, though its navy was controversially crippled at Mers el-Kebir. Dissent against this government was suppressed by the Milice under the control of Pierre Laval. This government attempted to gain legitimacy by appointing the hero of the battle of Verdun as its figurehead. Philippe P\u00b4etain headed, for the point, what French government that collaborated with the Nazis?", "answer": "<b> Vichy</b> France (prompt on France)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this state, George Pickett\u2019s decision to attend a fish bake led to the fall of the Five Forks railway junction. This state\u2019s Henrico County was the site of a diversionary attack at Deep Bottom, as Ambrose Burnside attempted to detonate a mine behind enemy forces and initiate the Battle of the Crater. In this state, the capture of Petersburg was vital in forcing the surrender of the Confederacy. For the point, name this US state where the Confederate capital of Richmond was located.", "answer": "<b> Virginia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The work of James Ensor includes many of these objects in the shape of skulls or cartoonish faces. Two of these objects are used to represent the muses Thalia and Melpomene [mel-pom-eh-nee]. The heads of 2 nude women are thought to be representations of these objects from Africa in Picasso\u2019s painting,<em> Les</em> <em>Desmoiselles d\u2019Avignon</em>. For the point, name these objects used in ritual dance traditions in Africa and to cover the faces of ancient Greek actors.", "answer": "<b> mask</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "When a ruler of this country won the 1739 Battle of Karnal, he stole the Koh-i-Noor Diamond and the Peacock Throne. After Abbas III was deposed, the Afsharid Dynasty was founded in this country by the aforementioned Nader Shah. This country\u2019s capital was moved to Isfahan by Abbas the Great, the fifth Shah of a dynasty that installed Twelver Shia Islam as this country\u2019s official religion. The Safavid Dynasty ruled, for the point, what Middle Eastern country that moved its capital in 1796 to Tehran?", "answer": "<b> Iran</b> (accept<b> Persia</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "From 1935 to 1949, this phenomenon occurred in China because English printing presses outpaced those of Chiang Kai-Shek\u2019s government; that instance of this phenomenon ended with the adoption of the renminbi. Eviction of white farmers by Robert Mugabe\u2019s government contributed to a major instance of this phenomenon in 1990s Zimbabwe that resulted in the creation of 100-billion-dollar bank notes. For the point, name this phenomenon in which currency is devalued and prices rise.", "answer": "(hyper)<b>inflation</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "A route used in this industry began in Fort Belknap and was named after Charles Goodnight and Oliver Loving. Another route used in this industry was established by Jesse Chisholm. Railroad facilities were built for use in this industry in Abilene and Kansas City, which shipped cargo to stockyards in Chicago. The development of barbed wire ended the era of massive drives in, for the point, what industry consisting of western ranchers?", "answer": "<b> cattle</b> industry (accept anything to do with<b> cow</b>s; prompt on meat or livestock industry; prompt on agriculture)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Wolfgang von Kempelen built a machine that purported to perform this action. In 1949, Claude Shannon published the first paper describing how a computer could be taught to perform this activity. Leonhard Euler worked on, but did not solve, a problem concerning finding a Hamiltonian path for the\u201ctour\u201d of one of the pieces used in this game. IBM\u2019s computer Deep Blue won a 1996 match of this game against Garry Kasparov, a Grand Master. For the point, name this strategy game played with knights, pawns, and kings.", "answer": "playing<b> chess</b> Page 4", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {"question": "This site first became commercialized thanks to a rivalry between the Desmond Service Company and the founders of Camp Curry. The Wawona Tree in this site\u2019s Mariposa Grove contained a tunnel for cars to pass through, but fell in 1969. This site was designated as a national park following a three-day camping trip near Glacier Point taken by John Muir and Theodore Roosevelt. Half Dome and El Capitan are found in, for the point, what national park in the Sierra Nevada range of California?", "answer": "<b> Yosemite</b> National Park", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "These weapons were deployed by both sides during the Battle of Raphia, although those of Antiochus III ultimately proved superior. The Roman cavalry was forced to retreat after Pyrrhus deployed this weapon against them at the Battle of Heraclea. Persian masters of these weapons were called<em> mahouts</em>, and they were used at the Battle of Gaugamela by Darius III, who deployed them as cavalry against Alexander the Great. Hannibal famously crossed the Alps with, for the point, what tusked war animal?", "answer": "war<b> elephant</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A series of attacks on bailiffs in this country led to a revolt known as the Dacke War. It conducted a series of attacks on its neighbor Poland-Lithuania in a campaign called the Deluge. This country captured parts of Pomerania and broke the power of the Hanseatic League. Its most famous ruler intervened in the Thirty Years\u2019 War on the Protestant side until his death at the Battle of Lutzen. For the point, name this home of Gustavus Adolphus, who ruled from Stockholm.", "answer": "<b> Sweden</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Three companies partially named after this company were part of the Seven Sisters, which dominated their industry in the mid-20th century. Muckraker Ida Tarbell wrote a lengthy history of this company, which was split into 34 separate entities after it was prosecuted under the Sherman Antitrust Act in 1911. This company grew due to horizontal integration of refining and tanker shipping firms. For the point, name this oil company founded by John D. Rockefeller.", "answer": "<b> Standard Oil</b> Company, Incorporated", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this novel, Mrs Dilber and Joe steal the protagonist\u2019s bedclothes while he has a series of journeys guided by figures like Ignorance and Want. This novel exposed the plight of \u201cragged school\u201d children to wealthy Victorians by praising the generosity of Mr Fezziwig and exposing the regrets of Jacob Marley. This novel\u2019s protagonist meets ghosts representing the present, past, and future, who inspire him to help Bob Cratchit and Tiny Tim. For the point, name this novel by Charles Dickens in which Ebenezer Scrooge discovers the true meaning of Christmas.", "answer": "A<b> Christmas Carol</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "These figures were jointly granted a title by Pope Alexander VI, who also granted them land with the bull<em> Inter caetera</em>. One of these figures was crowned after the Treaty of Alc\u00b4a\u00b8covas with the support of the other. The conquest of Granada was completed during the reigns of these two monarchs, who expelled their country\u2019s Jews with the Alhambra Decree. For the point, name these two Catholic Monarchs of Spain who authorized Christopher Columbus to sail to the New World.", "answer": "<b> Ferdinand</b> II of Aragon<b> and Isabella</b> I of Castile (accept in either order; prompt on \u201cCatholic Monarchs\u201d before mentioned) Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In the first battle of this war, Sidney Reilly sold maps of a harbor\u2019s minefield to the aggressors, who unintentionally launched a sneak attack when their declaration of war was preceded by a torpedo volley on Port Arthur. Theodore Roosevelt won the Nobel Peace Prize for negotiating an end to this war in the Treaty of Portsmouth. The Baltic fleet was crushed at the Battle of Tsushima in, for the point, what war fought between a European and an Asian power in the early 20th century?", "answer": "<b> Russo-Japanese</b> War Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}